[Music]
hi everyone we're back for our first
episode of the usada pitch in 2022 and
my first guest of the year is jeff cook
usada's general counsel thanks for
taking the time jeff thanks for having
me avery
with the 2022 winter games in progress
jeff is joining us to talk about the
game's name for usada so jeff during the
games we're often asked if we're super
busy like the usopc can you actually
speak to usada's role in operations
during the olympics and paralympics well
you're absolutely right avery it's a
it's a frequent question we get and a
lot of times people are surprised to
learn that as compared to the usopc or
other sport organizations who are
running an event
usada is relatively quiet during the
event
and it's important to keep in mind that
usada is independent from the usopc and
sport in general and so while sport
organizations certainly have a lot going
on during events that they're organizing
uh usada actually intensifies its
efforts in the lead up in the months
leading up to those events by increasing
testing because that's the time when
athletes could be using performance
enhancing drugs that will benefit them
during those events
that's not to say that testing doesn't
still occur during the events it does
but that testing is often coordinated by
the importance
perfect so you mentioned independence
can you talk more about how usada is
connected to the usopc
certainly so
uh just to step back usada is the
congressionally recognized national
anti-doping organization for the united
states and as such we operate the
anti-doping programs for olympic and
paralympic sports
now to do that we receive funding from
the government and we also receive
funding through a contract with the
usopc
but that but we are still independent
from both the government and the usmc
and as a non-profit organization
our goal is to make decisions and do
what will have the most impact in the
fight against doping
not based on politics or a bottom line
so what will our role be for la 2028
does it change
well if we're involved with anti-doping
efforts for la 2028 we would of course
do everything in our power to make it
the cleanest games ever
it should be the benchmark for clean
sport at the elite level and we'll we'll
partner with law enforcement to ensure
that the rod chinkoff anti-doping act
which criminalizes doping conspiracies
is fully enforced and we will be open
and available to work with
the international testing agency and
international federations
and wada to ensure testing is robust
both
during the games and also in the lead-up
to the games
fantastic well thanks for talking
through this today jeff well thanks
again for having me avery it was a
pleasure
stay tuned we'll be back for another
episode of the usada pitch soon
[Music]
you